{"tossups": [{"question": "Residents of this state often bake a many-layered cake called bebinca for Christmas. Those residents of this state also prepare an alcoholic beverage from cashews called feni. A close relative of psychedelic trance music is named for this state because it was developed by people in its beach town of Anjuna. The body of St. Francis Xavier is stored in this state's Basilica of Bom Jesus. Daman and Diu [Dee-oo] were formerly part of this state when it was a union territory. The curry dish (*) vindaloo originated in this state. Konkani is an official language in this state, alongside Marathi [muh-RAH-tee]. Panaji is the capital of this state, whose largest city is named for Vasco da Gama. Maharashtra and Karnataka surround this state. For 10 points, name this Indian state which was a former Portuguese colony.", "answer": "Goa", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "If the roots of the characteristic polynomial of an SHO [\"S-H-O\"] are related by application of this function, [read slowly] c is less than root 4 m k, and the SHO is underdamped. Applying this function to a unitary matrix gives its inverse, while applying it to a Hermitian matrix gives its transpose. This function of the root of a real-coefficient polynomial always yields another root. Multiplying a (*) complex number by this function of itself gives the square of its magnitude. Applying this function is equivalent to flipping the sign of the argument. Geometrically, this operation is a reflection about the real axis, and it's often denoted by a horizontal overbar. For 10 points, name this operation that flips the sign of a complex number's imaginary part.", "answer": "complex conjugation [accept word forms like complex conjugate]", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In the second measure of a work by a composer from this country, clarinets and brass synthesizers enter with a rapid three-note ostinato; that work is marked \"delirando.\" Decrescendoing low strings open the \"The Anfortas Wound\" second movement of a work by a composer from this country titled for a Schoenberg textbook. The latter of two \"fanfares for orchestra,\" written for the Great Woods Festival by a composer from this country, includes polyrhythms in the three (*) woodblocks and is titled Short Ride in a Fast Machine. That composer from this country memorialized 9/11 survivors in On The Transmigration of Souls. For 10 points, name this country home to the post-minimalist composer of operas like Nixon in China, John Adams.", "answer": "United States of America [accept America or the USA]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A New York newspaper summarized this battle as one side \"assaulting its jailer, but is still in jail.\" One side in this battle made three 180 degree turns, sending its battlecruisers on a \"death ride.\" Another side in this battle deployed to port from 6 rows of 4, crossing the enemy T. The HMS Revenge and HMS Agincourt sighted the Seydlitz during this battle, but did not attack. Although he was initially able to sink the Indefatigable, Reinhard (*) Scheer withdrew to Wilhelmshaven after losing to John Jellicoe in this battle, thus not allowing the British to destroy their fleet. This battle is known as the \"clash of the Dreadnoughts.\" For 10 points, name this battle fought in the North Sea off the coast of Denmark, the largest naval battle of World War I.", "answer": "Battle of Jutland [or Battle of Skagerrak]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A professor in a novel by this author hears telephones ring while out on a run and is told to save Marjorie Stubbs from a bomb. The narrator of another novel by this author distinguishes between \"thin\" and \"hidden\" examples of the title entities, which are named after women. The protagonist of a novel by this author meets an expert in Cimmerian languages named (*) Professor Uzzi-Tuzii while trying to get past the first chapter of books. Marco Polo discusses the title entities of a novel by this author with Kublai Khan. A novel by this author sees the protagonist fall in love with Ludmilla and is written in second-person. For 10 points, name this Italian author of Invisible Cities and If on a winter's night a traveler.", "answer": "Italo Calvino", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Saul Kirpke used the \"quus\" [kwuhss] function to demonstrate a rule-following paradox after reading one of this man's works. This philosopher criticized G.E. Moore's statement \"here is a hand\" to start his essay On Certainty. In one work, this philosopher introduced the idea that \"what we cannot speak of, we must pass over in silence\"; that work also introduced the \"picture theory of language.\" This philosopher demonstrated the incoherency of (*) \"private languages\" by having people define the contents of a box containing a beetle in Philosophical Investigations. For 10 points, name this Austrian philosopher and author of Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus.", "answer": "Ludwig Wittgenstein", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "One of these objects is hidden on Mexico Street by the narrator after he realizes that the \"best place to hide a leaf is in a forest.\" A footnote to a story describes a location containing these objects as \"pointless\" and was said by Letizia Alvarex de Toledo. The narrator of a story receives one of these objects from a Scottish salesman who got it from the \"outskirts of Bikaner.\" Greedy individuals search for prophetic examples of these objects called (*) \"Vindications\" in another short story. Purifiers attempts to search for the \"Crimson Hexagon\" in a story about these objects. For 10 points, name these objects which are found in a Jorge Luis Borges story about the library of Babel.", "answer": "books [accept \"The Book of Sand\"]", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This was the highest position held by a person who lost support in a presidential campaign after being supported by the KKK at the 1924 Democratic convention. The nomination of Roger Taney [TAWny] to hold this position, which was also held by William McAdoo, was the first to be rejected by the Senate. As a reward for eventually supporting Abraham Lincoln at the 1860 Convention, Salmon (*) Chase was given this position. The first holder of this position, which was later held by Albert Gallatin, proposed a tax on alcohol which led to the Whiskey Rebellion, and also proposed assuming the debts of states after the Revolutionary War. Janet Yellen currently holds, for 10 points, what cabinet position that looks over the US Mint and the Internal Revenues Service?", "answer": "Secretary of the Treasury", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "For a system of charges, the multipole expansion is found by using the law of cosines and writing this quantity in terms of Legendre polynomials. The Laplacian of this quantity equals negative volumetric charge density over the permittivity of free space, according to Poisson's equation. Thevenin's [TAY-vuh-nanz] theorem allows any linear circuit to be simplified into a resistor and source of this quantity. This scalar quantity is constant in a (*) conductor. The difference in this quantity is often found by taking the negative line integral of an electric field between two points. This quantity can be stepped up and down using a transformer. For 10 points, name this quantity that, according to Ohm's law, equals current times resistance.", "answer": "voltage [or electric potential or scalar potential; prompt on V; do not accept or prompt on \"potential energy\" or \"vector potential\"]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One of these works shows a close up of a human ear under rippling water. Another of these works drew confusion because it consists solely of an unadorned photograph of a cow in a field. One of these works depicts two businessmen shaking hands outside the Warner Brothers studio, with one of the two men on fire, while in another of these works an inflatable pig hovers above Battersea power station. One of these works consists of an array of white (*) bricks with grey mortar in a depiction of the title construct. The most famous of these artworks shows a triangular prism on a black background dispersing a beam of white light into a rainbow. For 10 points, name these artworks that appear on the front of \"The Wall\" and \"The Dark Side of the Moon\".", "answer": "Pink Floyd album covers [or Pink Floyd cover art, prompt on album covers or albums by asking \"for what band?\"]", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "In this work, Hussein believes that he is a pen, and so slits his own throat trying to sharpen himself. Another character in this work strands his mother on the roof so he can crash a wedding, and later makes a fortune by alternating sending idols and missionaries to China. That title character of this play encounters the Boyg while fleeing from imps and nixies, and pleads with the devil to save him from being melted down by the (*) Button-Moulder. This play begins with the title character telling his mother Ase an elaborate yarn about a reindeer hunt, and ends with Solveig [SOUL-vay] singing to him. An encounter with the Dovre King of the Trolls in this play was the inspiration for \"In the Hall of the Mountain King,\" part of a musical work based on it. For 10 points, name this Ibsen verse play, the inspiration for a suite by Edvard Grieg.", "answer": "Peer Gynt", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This country's DOI-CODI [doy koh jee] secret police tortured Vladimir Herzog to death. After a series of arrests by Newton Ishii in this country, the conglomerate Odebrecht [oh-duh-bresh] was renamed to Novonor. After a leader of this country shot himself at the Catete [caw-tay-chee] Palace, Pl\u00ednio Salgado returned from exile to reform its Integralist Party. \"Fifty years of progress in five\" was promised by (*) Juscelino Kubitschek [zhoo-say-lee-no koo-beach-check], who commissioned Oscar Niemeyer to design this country's capital. Sergio Moro led this country's Operation Car Wash, which led to the impeachment of its first female president. This country was led by Get\u00falio Vargas and Dilma Rousseff. For 10 points, Jair Bolsonaro leads what Portuguese-speaking South American country?", "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil [or Brasil]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One of this author's poems describes a man whose \"cheek was like a rose / In the snow\" until he was cut down by \"the pruning-knife of Time.\" Another poem by this author tells of a song heard \"through the deep caves of thought.\" In one poem, this author laments that \"The meteor of the ocean air / Shall sweep the clouds no more!\", and proposes giving the title object to (*) \"the god of storms / The lightning and the gale!\" In addition to a poem about a \"ship of pearl\" which \"sails the unshadowed main,\" this author wrote a poem that begins \"Ay, tear her tattered ensign down!\" and helped prevent the USS Constitution from being decommissioned. For 10 points, name this fireside poet from Boston who wrote \"The Chambered Nautilus\" and \"Old Ironsides.\"", "answer": "Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr. [the first line refers to \"The Last Leaf\"]", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One building by this architect is a cylindrical building with a brick exterior and a skylight, the only window, directly above the altar. This architect designed a structure for Yale's campus that is known as \"the whale\" for its doubly curved form. A building designed by this architect of the Ingalls Rink features a thin-shell roof supported by four Y-shaped piers, and another in the shape of a one-eighth sphere supported by glass curtain walls on (*) MIT's campus. This architect designed a stainless steel arch in the shape of a catenary curve that is located on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, in addition to the TWA Flight Center and the Kresge Auditorium. For 10 points, name this Finnish-American architect who designed the Gateway Arch.", "answer": "Eero Saarinen [do not accept or prompt on \"Eliel Saarinen\"]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Neutron capture therapy treats tumors by first using an isotope of this element to absorb neutrons. Alternating this element and nitrogen in a six-membered ring forms \"inorganic benzene.\" An acid of this element is used to perform an anti-Markovnikov addition of an alcohol to an alkene. A palladium complex catalyzes the cross-coupling between acids of this element and organohalides in the (*) Suzuki reaction. The wurtzite form of this element's nitride is harder than diamond. This element's trifluoride is a Lewis acid which is planar because it has only 3 bonding domains, since this element violates the octet rule. For 10 points, name this first metalloid with atomic number 5.", "answer": "boron [or B]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A city of this name was defeated by the Han general Li Guangli in the War of the Heavenly Horses; that city was known by the epithet \"Eschate,\" or \"furthest.\" A city of this name was located in modern-day Kandahar, and contained a copy of the Edicts of Ashoka. That city of this name in ancient Arachosia was ceded to Chandragupta Maurya along with 500 elephants by (*) Seleucus I Nicator [suh-LYOO-kus one nigh-KAY-ter]. The Eastern-most city of this name was founded after the death of a certain animal at the battle of the Hydaspes River. The most prominent city with this name contained a huge lighthouse constructed by Ptolemy II. For 10 points, give this name of cities in Asia Minor, the Middle East, and North Africa that were named for their founder, who rode the horse Bucephalus and conquered the Persian Empire in the 4th-century BCE.", "answer": "Alexandria [accept Alexandria Eschate; accept Alexandria Arachosia; accept Alexandria Bucephalous]"}, {"question": "One recurring structure in this organelle resembles parking garage ramps and is named for Mark Terasaki. The SERCA pump regulates calcium ion concentration in this organelle, as does calsequestrin. The signal recognition particle targets proteins to this organelle's translocon. This organelle is the site of N-linked glycosylation. Vesicles leaving this organelle are tagged with (*) COPII [\"C O P 2\"]. One type of this organelle is found wrapped around myofibrils in muscle cells. Like the Golgi apparatus, this organelle is composed of a network of flattened discs called cisternae. This membranous organelle is continuous with the nuclear envelope. For 10 points, name this organelle, classified based on the presence of ribosomes as either \"rough\" or \"smooth.\"", "answer": "endoplasmic reticulum [or ER; accept rough or smooth ER, accept sarcoplasmic reticulum or SR]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This religion's principle of eternal progression is summarized \"as man is, God once was; as God is, man may become.\" Members of this faith are asked \"Are you a full-tithe payer?\" and \"Do you understand and obey the Word of Wisdom?\" in temple recommend interviews. This religion's Plan of Salvation describes the Telestial, Terrestrial and Celestial Kingdoms of Glory. This religion's \"standard works\" include the (*) Doctrine and Covenants and the Pearl of Great Price. This religion is symbolized by the Angel Moroni, who members believe revealed the locations of seer stones and golden plates to its founder. For 10 points, name this Christian denomination founded by Joseph Smith and headquartered in Salt Lake City, Utah.", "answer": "The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints [or LDS; or Mormonism]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "One character with this last name describes crying by a bag of dog biscuits after being confronted by the narrator of one book. Another character with this last name, who was likely inspired by Ginevra King, asks for her infant daughter to be \"a beautiful little fool.\" That character with this last name falls in love with an AEF officer stationed in Camp Taylor near Louisville. A man with this last name misleads a (*) car mechanic into murdering a character in a swimming pool. The home of a couple with this last name has a \"green light\" that the title character of one book reaches out to. While driving a yellow car, a woman with this last name accidentally runs over Myrtle Wilson. For 10 points, name this last name shared by Tom and Daisy in The Great Gatsby.", "answer": "Buchanan [accept Tom Buchanan; accept Daisy Buchanan]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The Politics, Culture, and Class of this event were explored in a study by Lynn Hunt. One book concerning this event claimed that \"the most wonderful things are brought about in many instances, by means the most absurd and ridiculous.\" Thousands of prisoners were murdered in this event's September Massacres, as recounted in a three-volume history of it by Thomas Carlyle. Edmund (*) Burke wrote a series of Reflections criticizing this event which argues from expenditures outlined by Finance Minister Jacques Necker. This event's \"Radical\" phase often begins with the storming of the Tuileries [tweel-ree] Palace in 1792. For 10 points, name this event which overthrew Louis XVI and began its country's First Republic.", "answer": "French Revolution", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}], "bonuses": []}